Can Carlos stand and clean?
Sylvia with Crown Princess Victoria and Prince Daniel have arrived.
As well as call him to kill the ocean to stand.
Keep their seats.
And now we will hear March in the Major by Wolfgang Amidus Mosut,
which is the music that is played when the loritz entered the stage.
The music is played when the loritz entered the stage.
Everybody rises for the loritz.
The first in line is Ezra Amouho, the physics lawyer followed by his physics colleague, Loritz Donna Stritchand.
Frances Arnold, one of the chemistry lawyers with George Smith and Gregory Winter,
by her side to the right, also chemistry loritz.
And then we have James Allison and Tazuko Honjo, this year's medicine loritz.
And to the far right there we have William Northhausen, Paul Romer, economics.
The first in line is the
first in line with the loritz.
And then we have the first in line with the loritz.
The first in line with the loritz.
All in all 12 loritz this year, including the peace loritz, Dennis McQuigua and Nadia Murad,
who earlier today received the peace prize in Oslo.
Your Majesty's, your Royal Highness's, esteemed Nobel loritz, ladies and gentlemen.
Call her in a clinch of the Nobel Foundation.
It's a great pleasure for me to welcome you all to this year's Nobel Prize Award Ceremony.
In particular, I would like to welcome the Nobel loritz and their families to this ceremony.
Earlier today in Oslo, the knee mucwege and Nadia Murad
were awarded the Nobel Peace Prize for their efforts to end the use of sexual violence as a weapon of war and armed conflict.
Through this prize, the Norwegian Nobel Committee reminds us that human rights must include also rights of women.
Too often women have been violated in conflicts as a way of disrupting a society.
Words cannot describe the horrors that Nadia Murad has lived through,
but we should be grateful that she has decided to share her story with us as a call for action.
Dr. Dene McQuigua has likewise shown exceptional courage and persistence when he, at great personal risk, has alleviated the suffering of so many women in the Congo.
Alfred Nobel's vision was to reward those who have made the greatest benefit to humankind.
In science, literature and peace, and thereby have contributed to a better world.
Undoubtedly, the world has, in many ways, become a better place since the end of the 19th century when Alfred Nobel lived.
However, in recent years, we have unfortunately seen new dangerous tendencies on the rise.
While the Paris Agreement is assigned at the question of global warming is taking seriously,
it is deeply worrying that influential world leaders are denying the connection despite of overwhelming scientific evidence between our lifestyle and climate change
and preventing the necessary actions from being taken.
Also in other fields, we see that facts, observations, and information are distorted or ignored.
We see how nationalism and isolationism are increasing, with restrictions in trade, culture, and exchange, and movement across borders.
Together, this endangers the world has been knowet.
Science offers counter-movement to the isolationistic and fact-resistant tendencies we see.
It has no borders and scientists often move between countries.
Science is our times lingua-franca and can form bridges between countries and cultures.
The importance of research is therefore not only limited to the generation of new knowledge,
but it serves a more general role, providing a common ground for interactions between people all over the world.
Moreover, modern science does not only involve skeptical inquiring, but is also often led by an ethos of openness and tolerance.
Today, we do not only celebrate the Nobel Prize.
It is also 70 years ago that the Universal Declaration of Human Rights was adopted by the United Nations.
And 50 years in Rene Kassan received the Nobel Prize for his work with the Declaration.
This serves to remind us that one of the reasons that modern society has progressed is that it has created a set of institutions and instruments that formalize this progress.
Human rights is one of these as is science and democracy.
But again, we cannot take these institutions and instruments for granted.
We are all aware of the increasing questioning of universal human rights, freedom of speech, and academic independence.
All values closely connected with what a Nobel Prize stands for.
This is deeply troubling since we risk a regression to a time before they existed, to a time ruled by ignorance, prejudice, and barbarism.
The now more than 900 Nobel laureates and that achievements are a source of inspiration to us all.
We have visited museums in Stockholm and Oslo, various events in different countries, and through our digital channels with millions of followers, we are reaching out all over the globe to tell their stories.
To further enhance our outreach activities, we have been working hard with support from the Ellen Passion Family Foundation and the Knuten Alice Valenberg Foundation and many other donors to achieve a Nobel Center.
We would like to take this opportunity to thank them as well as the architects, David Chippewfield and Kristoff Felger for their support and commitment.
Despite the setback we now have had with the decisions taken by the new ruling majority in Stockholm, we are prepared to continue to work for this idea.
It is simply to go to be stopped.
However, given what has happened, we have to be clear. If Stockholm is going to get a Nobel Center, strong concrete and reliable support from the city of Stockholm, as well as from the governmental Sweden, will be needed.
Scientific breakthroughs of the kind we honour today are of fostered by creating strong environments and by giving excellent scientists freedom independence and long term funding.
Such creative milleures become fertile for new ideas through being open to a diversity of skills, experiences and cultural backgrounds and through letting young scientists speak their mind.
In strong scientific environments, the focus is often on basic research, that is curiosity-driven research which does not aim at solving a practical problem, but only aims at answering interesting and important questions.
Max Planck, the 1918 Nobel Laureate in physics, went so far as to say, scientific discovery and scientific knowledge have been achieved only by those who have gone in pursuit of it without any practical purpose whatsoever in view.
Remarkably, however, many basic research discoveries have later been proven to have practical usefulness, often in unexpected areas.
In this way, advances in basic science become part of the progress that Alfred Nobel wishes to see.
The production of new knowledge just joins the struggle for human rights in these awards, which we hope can inspire in particular young people to make even more remarkable contributions for the benefit of humankind.
Thank you for listening, and once again, most welcome to this year's Nobel Prize Award ceremony.
Seth Knoll and Henry Helene Sherman of the Board of the Nobel Foundation, before the first prizes are to be handed over by his majesty, the King.
The first laureate to receive it will be Geramo, but first some music by Claude Debussy, French composer.
The second laureate to receive it will be Geramo, the first laureate to receive it.
The third laureate to receive it will be Geramo, the first laureate to receive it.
Claude Bussis, Claude Lune, perhaps especially appreciated by this year's physics lawyer, Geramo, also from France born in 1944 in Albeville.
At the time of affiliation, worked at Ecole Polytechnique in Palaisau in France and a speech now about my studies.
Ladies and gentlemen, sunlight is essential to life on earth and it gets better and better at harnessing its energy.
We also use light in many other ways today of employing a laser as the light source.
For example, in the late New York Times, the barcode series on a laser.
This year's hella, the physics honors two inventions in laser, laser, laser, physics, and that have an infinite, for a new, born, brilliant understanding that I use light.
This method has given us light-based tools with applications in medicine and other fields.
Arthur Askin is being rewarded for the invention of optical tweezers and their application to biological systems.
This invention is based on the ability of light to exert a force on matter known as radiation pressure.
The possibility of using light via this force to move physical objects may make one thing of star trek and tractor beams and sound like pure science fiction.
This is the case with the light source.
We can feel that sun beams carry energy, they make us warm, but we cannot feel any small push.
The force of this sunlight is too weak to do so.
The laser beam is actually strong enough to move microscopically particles.
As it turned out, laser light could not only move such particles, but could also be made to grab them by focusing the beam with the help of a lens.
This marked the birth of the optical tweezers, an elegant tool, that has gained a broad range of applications and that lets us hold onto and move objects such as living cells without touching them.
The American homophilicians, the method, has been successfully used to investigate various components of biological cells.
Among other things, providing us with knowledge about the mechanics of tiny molecular motors and perform vital work inside these cells.
Shurram Ho and Donna Strickland, a robot of an invention called the Cherk Pass Amplification or CPL.
This is a method for creating extremely intense short passes of laser light.
Efforts to create more intense laser passes have been on the way since the first laser was built in 1960.
By the mid-1980s, these experiments had reached an impasse, since the intensity of the laser light destroyed the amplifying material itself.
Using their acetate of made Ho and Strickland were able to get around this limitation.
The strategy was simple and elegant.
First stretch out the laser pass in time, thereby reducing its intensity and the allow you to be amplified.
Finally, compress the pass again to its original length of time, but now a much higher intensity.
The numbers, method, changed landscape of research about high-intensity lasers, from something that had been powered out in a few large laboratory places,
to something that could be done in many places around the world.
Leading to powerful search in development.
Iac's pursuit of short and short passes has enabled researchers to move closer to the atosec level,
which means one billionth of a billionth of a second.
This opens the way for studying the movements of electrons in the atoms and molecules.
Till the number of applications of laser passes are being made possible by the C8 and E1.
One example is eye surgery for correcting near-sightedness in which laser passes serve as ultra-prissue surgical tool.
Dr. Raskin, Professor Murrow, Professor Strickland,
you have been awarded the 2018 Nobel Prize in Physics for your groundbreaking inventions in the field of laser physics.
On behalf of the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, it's my honor and great pleasure to convey to you our warmest congratulations.
I now ask you to step forward to receive your Nobel prizes from the hands of his majesty, Dekin.
I welcome Professor Michael Erschkin to receive the prize on behalf of his father, Arthur Erschkin.
That was the presentation speech by Professor Anders Eerbeck, member of the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences.
I wonder what the king might be saying now.
Perhaps say hello to your father. He's probably watching this.
Michael Erschkin, son of Arthur Erschkin, receiving this year's physics prize.
Michael Erschkin, himself a professor of OTS.
Shachamahu, born in France, also receives his prize.
And Donna Theos Strickland, born in 1959 in Ontario, Canada, receives her part of 2018 Nobel Physics prize.
And now some music by Charles D. Griffs.
We will hear soloist Kristina Nilsson and the Royal Stockholm Philharmonic Orchestra.
The piece is the lament of Ian the Proud from the three poems of Fiona McLeod.
The piece is the lament of the three poems of Fiona McLeod.
The piece is crying that I live in the wind.
And the sound of my dream.
I know not what it is, but I'm the more I'm the sure.
The piece is crying that I live in the wind.
And the sound of my dream.
And the other half is jointly awarded to George Smith of University of Missouri in the United States.
And now we will enjoy some more music.
And now some more music.
Thank you from Stockholm.